<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Jacob, the plain man, wrestling with God until the break of the day and prevailing in the light thereof for perfect victory and dominign [sic] over Esau, the rough and cunning man ... / [by] Laurence Steel.</title>
            <author>Steel, Laurence, d. 1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61380</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5378</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32673</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12744909</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12744909</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93225</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61380)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93225)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1537:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Jacob, the plain man, wrestling with God until the break of the day and prevailing in the light thereof for perfect victory and dominign [sic] over Esau, the rough and cunning man ... / [by] Laurence Steel.</title>
                  <author>Steel, Laurence, d. 1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conversion.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Quaker authors.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93225:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93225:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>JACOB THE Plain Man Wreſtling with God un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Break of the Day, and prevalling in the Lig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ereof, for perfect VICTORY and DOMINIGN over ESAU THE Rough &amp; Cunning Man, And over all that would hinder him from going up to <hi>Bethel,</hi> the Houſe of God, to ſacrifice unto him in the Place where he firſt appear'd unto him.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="approbation">
               <body>
                  <p>Whereby all may ſee, how I was after long Wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with, and ſeeking the Lord, brought off from Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing and Preaching that for Goſpel which made not free from ſin in this Life, that I might come to know the Light and Life of Jeſus manifeſt in me for the Deſtroying the Works of the Devil, and giving Power to ſupplant &amp; overcome all that would hinder from going up to the Mountain of the Lord's Houſe to Worſhip and Serve him in the Life and Purity of his own Spirit, which is bleſſed for evermore; Whoſe Outward Name is</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Laurence Steel.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1677.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:93225:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THeſe things were required of me to give forth to be read in the Fear of the Lord, which (if kept to) will make a right Application of all unto thy own Eſtate and Condition, either by way of Condemning thee or Juſtifying of thee; and may, if in Singleneſs of Heart thou readeſt, help to open thy Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Diſcerning of theſe things, which the Lord (through the Dayes of Judgment and Tryals that are paſt, and thoſe that are yet to come) hath and will more and more ſupplant &amp; overturn, and what he hath and will yet more and more eſtabliſh and exalt in the room thereof, that ſo thou mayſt come timely to eſcape the one, and to joyn unto the other, leſt the Day of the Lord, which will be as a Thief in the Night, overtake thee unawares.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93225:2"/>
            <head>A TESTIMONY TO THE Goſpel of Chriſt Jeſus: AS Anciently preached and believed in by the Primitive APOSTLES and CHRISTIANS; with the Manner of my coming to witneſs and receive the ſame.</head>
            <p>THe Goſpel of Chriſt (as it was preached and witneſſed by the Primitive <hi>Chriſtians</hi>) is the Power of God unto Salvation unto them that do believe, in which Goſpel the Wrath of God is revealed from Heaven againſt all (mark, All) Ungodlineſs and Unrighteouſneſs of Men, who hold the Truth (which is the Goſpel that ſhould ſave them) in Unrighteouſneſs: (So the Truth is in Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Men, and teſtifieth againſt their Unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, in which it is by them held down and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, which keeps them from witneſſing Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance thereby.) And in this Goſpel there is no Glad-tidings to any in Unrighteouſneſs, nor Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in Ungodlineſs, but Wrath revealed againſt it, and abideth upon all ſuch as hold the Truth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, until they come to bow to the Wrath of God
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93225:3"/> which is revealed in them for the cutting down of all Unrighteouſneſs and Ungodlineſs, and for the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Truth which is held therein; and ſuch come through the righteous Judgments of God to know that Righteouſneſs, which is Chriſt, the Power of God, to be revealed, for the removing and taking away of the Wrath that was upon them, and the bringing them to Life and Juſtification, who are hereby made Witneſſes, that <hi>what may be known of God,</hi> viz. of his Eternal Power, to ſanctifie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem out of Sin and Unrighteouſneſs, <hi>is manifeſt in them;</hi> for God hath ſhewed it unto them to be his Goſpel and Power unto Salvation, who do come from holding of the Truth in Unrighteouſneſs, to hold this Myſtery of Faith in a pure Conſcience; ſo this Goſpel of Chriſt, which is a Myſtery, was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted or ſhewed to the Primitive Saints to be within. And how was it ſhewed? Not by Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition from Man, or any outward Letter, but by Revelation; Therefore it is ſaid, <hi>The wrath of God is revealed</hi> (mark) and <hi>The Righteouſneſs of God is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed;</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> calls the Goſpel, which he received not by Tradition from any, <hi>The Revelation</hi> [mark] <hi>of his Son in him.</hi> And how was it that Chriſt came to be revealed in <hi>Paul,</hi> but by the Light, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the Brightneſs of the Sun, the outward na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Light, which Light was the Appearance of Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> which alſo inwardly ſhewed him, and prickt him for his Perſecution, which he ſaw not, nor was not judged for by the outward Letter of the Law, according to which he was blameleſs: And <hi>Paul</hi> being thus met with and ſtopt by a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Power and Authority then that by which he was
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93225:3"/> before acting, it was hard for him to kick againſt the Pricks of this Light; but he fell down, both he and his Companions, with their Commiſſion from the High Prieſt, and all their Letter Knowledge before this Light of Jeſus, which was greater then all; and here <hi>Paul</hi> lay until the Light that ſtruck him down ſaid unto him, <hi>Stand up;</hi> and in the riſing up, after he had known the inward Pricks and Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of the Lord, he came to receive a Power and Commiſſion, to turn the People from Darkneſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Light, which he elſe-where calls the <hi>Revelation of Chriſt in him;</hi> and when the Saints heard that <hi>Paul</hi> preached of and by virtue from Chriſt revealed in him, which Goſpel he once ſought to deſtroy, they glorified God in him [mark, in him] And this was and is the true Goſpel, and the manner of the Saints receiving of it, <hi>viz.</hi> by <hi>Revelation,</hi> not by <hi>Tradition</hi> from Men or Writings; and if an Angel from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſhould bring any other Goſpel, he was to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed: And this was and is the true Foundation, other then which no man can lay, upon which the Ancient <hi>Chriſtians</hi> built their Hope of Glory, <hi>viz.</hi> Chriſt in them, which was not another then Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> who was with them, and now came to be manifeſt in them for the deſtroying of the Works of the Enemy, that ſo he and his Works be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing caſt out, the Seed of God, which is Chriſt the greater Power, might only remain in perfect Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and Poſſeſſion of the Hearts, out of the good Treaſure whereof good Fruits and Works were to be brought forth to his Glory, who is bleſſed for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
            <p>Now, this Goſpel of Chriſt I could not meet with,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93225:4"/> or hear preached in any of the Profeſſions that I was converſant in, whoſe Faith was, that <hi>Revelation was ceaſed, and that there was not a total Ceſſation from Sin</hi> (which is the Work of the Devil) <hi>attainable in this Life, nor no ſuch Grace or Light given to Mankind, by which they might come to deny all Ungodlineſs, and all Worldly Luſts; but that, if the Converſation were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, yet there would be Luſt and Sin ſtill remaining within to the Life's end, from the Commiſſion whereof none could be fully freed by any Power or Strength, which God had given on this ſide the Grave.</hi> Nor did I receive this Goſpel by Tradition from Man, or any Writings, Learning or Wiſdom of my own, but from the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, who ſeparated me for his Service from the Womb, and placed his Fear in me, which incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me in the beginning of my dayes to ſeek his Glory &amp; Honour above the Pleaſures of this World, and by the Riches of his free Grace drew me out of thoſe Wayes in which many Children were walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Deſtruction; ſo that in the Feeling of the Movings and Strivings of his Spirit (which I plainly remember from the ſixth and ſeventh years of my Age) I often left my Companions and Recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that I was engaged with to ſeek ſome Place for Prayer, and for the eaſing of my Heart unto him, fearing that, if I anſwered not his Call at that time, I ſhould not feel the ſame drawing afterward, which ſometimes I found to my Sorrow; and the ſame Power conſtrained me to cry to him, To acquaint me with himſelf, and to convert me from every Evil Way and Work, which I was prone to, that I might gain others unto him, and if he called me to it, Dye for him, as I read many of the Martyrs,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93225:4"/> who were weak in themſelves, he enabled to do. And being devoted to the Miniſtry from my Birth by my Parents, who were zealous Profeſſors of the <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant</hi>-Way, they ſpared no Pains to inſtruct me in the Principles of that Religion, nor any Coſt for the Educating of me in the Knowledge of that Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that was eſteemed requiſite for that Work: So that about the twelfth year of my Age I was placed abroad with other Children at the School, by whoſe Example and Importunity I was drawn to ſpend my Leiſure-Hours in thoſe Sports and Paſtimes which were accounted harmleſs, and by Reaſon of my Earneſtneſs therein, I neglected to anſwer the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings of the Spirit of God, which was near me, and would often have kept me back from going with them, whoſe Vain Words and Actions were a Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then to me, or elſe would have taken me off ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the midſt of my Play, and called me to ſeek the Lord for my Soul, the Motions of which were day after day quenched by my Diſobedience, until, as to my Feeling, it had ceaſed to ſtrive with me; ſo that, when I went to pray or ſeek the Lord, my Heart was ſhut up, and my Words returned un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me again, and I ſtood as one ſmitten before the Lord, not being able many times to utter or bring forth a word, becauſe of the Guilt and Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that was upon me when I came to be retired from my <hi>Companions,</hi> which Guilt I heaped up for ſome years, until the Reckoning was high between <hi>me</hi> and the <hi>Lord,</hi> whoſe Judgments and Indignation ſo ſeized upon <hi>me</hi> at laſt, as that I knew not but <hi>I was forſaken forever, and had ſinned out the Day of my Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation,</hi> and would have bowed to any Terms for the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93225:5"/> Heaſt Hopes of Mercy, or eſcaping the <hi>Torments of Hell</hi> that were before me, or for the obtaining the Stirring and Strivings of the Spirit of God with me, as formerly I had felt it; but my Cry ſeemed to be ſhut out, ſo that my Life became a Burthen to me, and all that I enjoyed was imbittered by the <hi>Wrath</hi> and <hi>Judgments</hi> of the Lord, which followed me whereſoever I went, or whatſoever I did, ſo that there was no ſtrugling with it, or diverting of it, which brought a Waſting and Conſumption upon my Body, which I never fully recover'd to this time, &amp; this continu'd for many Moneths, in which I ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly open'd my heart to any but the Lord, who through his Chaſtizements and Rebukes, in which I did par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take in Meaſure with Chriſt in his Suffering &amp; Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, brought me by his Word of Power to ſome hope of Mercy, and eſcaping of his Wrath, not by juſtifying of me in my Sin, but clenſing me in Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure from Sin and the Love of it, which Tidings was more precious to me then the Gain of the whole World, though <hi>my Body</hi> was left very weak, and <hi>my Strength</hi> decayed, which in time was by the ſame Word reſtored to the Admiration of my Relations and Acquaintance, that knew me in my Sickneſs. And now my Fears and Diſtruſts were Baniſhed by the Riſings of the Life &amp; Spirit of God in me, which wrought more frequently and powerfully then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, drawing me into greater Watchfulneſs over my Thoughts, Words and Actions, and into an higher Abſtinence from the Pleaſure and Delights of this World, moving Me to reprove ſuch as diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured the Name of the Lord, or did offend &amp; grieve his Spirit by the Miſ-ſpending Time in Vanity,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93225:5"/> in which I ſpared no Relations or others; and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times I was conſtrained to Warn and Reprove pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and wanton People upon the Road, and to eaſe my ſelf in Evil Company by crying to the Lord, which brought a Fear and Dread upon them, and none durſt to with-ſtand the Power that was with me in any Reproof, Prayer or Exhortation, which was adminiſtred in the Denyal of <hi>my own Will,</hi> in which I never went without a certain Reward of Peace in <hi>my Boſome,</hi> which were the beſt Times that ever I knew before the Truth was clearly mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted to me, when I was not yet ſetled in any Form or Profeſſion, or obſerved any ſtinted Times or Way of Praying or ſeeking the Lord, but as by his Spirit he moved upon my Heart, at Home or Abroad, to cry unto him, I obeyed, wondering and admiring what that was which was ſo ſweet and pleaſant in its Incomes, and drew me into a daily waiting for it, as my Life, and by which I was broken and tendered in the receiving of every Mercy and Bleſſing as from the Lord, and burdened and wounded with what was dead and unſavoury. After which I was ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up to ſeek after a People with whom I might have Unity in the Feeling of the ſame Life and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of the ſame <hi>work</hi> which I had paſs'd through And in the Zeal of my Heart, as one raiſed from the Dead, that diligently minded the Improvement of the Time that I was intruſted with, I neglected no Oportunities in all Seaſons and Weathers, without regarding the Health of my Body, to go to hear ſuch as were eſteemed <hi>Lively Awakening Preachers,</hi> firſt of the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and then of the <hi>Independants,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom I joyned my ſelf as a Member, among
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93225:6"/> whom I felt a Meaſure of the Stirrings of the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, which brought Terror upon the Ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſeized many that were looſe and vain, with a Senſe of their Iniquity, and made them cry out under it, and raiſed thoſe Hungerings and Thirſtings after Righteouſneſs, which cauſed many to break forth in earneſt Cryes and Supplications unto God for Deliverance from the Bonds of Sin and Iniquity, which was become burdenſom unto them, &amp; for the obtaining of that righteouſneſs which was more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in their Eye then the Glories and Pleaſures of the World, which they ſeemed dead unto for a time: And with this Work I had Unity, and delighted to be with this People in the dayes of their Tenderneſs, and to ſpend Time in Prayer and Conference with them. After which, as we came to ſettle in the Form, and to ſtint and limit the Spirit of God, ſo I perceived a dying to the Life that moved and bubled up in us, and cauſed us to breath and cry to the Lord, ſo that, when we came together, we were full of Complaints of Dryneſs, Barrenneſs and Lukewarmneſs that we were come unto, and for want of thoſe living Breathings, which once we felt, which we were ready to believe that we ſhould never come out of theſe Complaints, to know per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Victory over our Corruptions here below; and here in the Integrity of my Heart, I rather blamed and judged my ſelf (even when I knew no real Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect by my ſelf) then to blame the Miniſtry and Way that was preached, until the Lord ſhewed me the true Reaſon and Cauſe not to be from my own Careleſneſs, in the Neglect of any preſcribed Means which I followed, but becauſe of the Shortneſs and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93225:6"/> Defect of that Goſpel in which there was no Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er declared of, that might free from Sin in this Life, nor Faith to believe in the Manifeſtation of Chriſt, who was come (not only to bind the Strong Man, which ſome of us knew for a time, until he came to break his Bonds, and get looſe again, but) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the ſeed of the Serpent, and his Works in us, which being <hi>deſtroy'd,</hi> ſo as not to remain longer in us we might come to be born of God, ſo as not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Sin, becauſe of the Seed of God, which is Chriſt Jeſus, remaining alone in us in full Power and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Dominion over the ſeed of the Serpent and his Works: But inſtead thereof, they declared of a Juſtification and Salvation by Chriſt which was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the remaining of the Enemy, and of his Works of Darkneſs and Defilement in them unto the Life's End, when the time of Redemption was paſt: So that after they had brought the People to a ſenſe of ſin and iniquity, and Deſire of Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, which was good and precious in its day, they could bring them to no further Perfection in this Life, then the laying again and again (as often as they performed any Duties or Services) the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Repentance from Dead Works, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with their beſt Services were poluted, and the laying again of the Foundation of Faith towards God, whom they profeſſed ſtill to be going towards, but could not come to him, having not their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences purged from Dead Works, which all muſt have that would offer up living Sacrifices, and work the Works of God, which are never to be repented of. And ſince (according to their Goſpel) a through clenſing from ſin was not to be effected in this Life, nor could not be after this Life, in which the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93225:7"/> of the Soul ceaſeth, they ſhould have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome Middle Place for the Accompliſhment of this neceſſary Work, without which there could be no Admiſſion into the Kingdom of God.</p>
            <p>And in the Senſe of that Decay of Life and Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualneſs, and that Earthlineſs that was got up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Profeſſors, who by their faſhioning themſelves according to the World, had loſt their Teſtimony for God, I eaſed my ſelf in the firſt publick Opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity that was offered me in <hi>London,</hi> the Place of my Nativity, from theſe Words of <hi>Paul, All ſeek their own things, and not the things of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and another time at a Faſt, from the Teſtimony of <hi>Jeremiah, Though</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> Samuel <hi>ſtood before me yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ould not my Heart be towards this People; caſt them out of my Sight, let them go forth:</hi> Which things were uttered not to pleaſe man, but to diſcharge my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, in the manifeſting thoſe Provocations, which was a Grief to ſee in ſuch as profeſſed Salvation and Redemption by Chriſt Jeſus, and yet were not to be diſtinguiſhed from them who made no Profeſſion of him; &amp; for my plain Dealing I met with much Love, and ſoliciting to come oftner among them. Thus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſought into the higheſt Profeſſions I could hear of, in which I was uprightly deſirous to know the utmoſt of what was to be found of Life and Purity, which did not amount to that Spiritualneſs, and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory over Sin which I looked for, in a People, and for which I was raiſed up; wherefore in Refuſal of more publick Imployments I accepted of a private Place in <hi>Dorſet-ſhire,</hi> where I was to tutor their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and pray and preach in the Family for ſuch a yearly Stipend, which when it came to be paid I
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93225:7"/> was not ſuffered to take any thing for preaching, which alſo I denyed in <hi>London:</hi> And in this Family where there were many of a ſeeking enquiring Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, I kept up the Family-Worſhip, according to the Practice and Example of the beſt reputed Chriſtians which I walkt ſtrictly by, and the Meeting on the <hi>Firſt Dayes,</hi> unto which many People came, until that I came to preach from thoſe Words <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. v. 12. <hi>For the Word of God is Quick and Powerful, and Sharper then any Two edged Sword, Piercing, even to the Dividing aſunder the Joynts and the Marrow;</hi> at the finiſhing of which Scripture, after I was retired into my Chamber the Word of the Lord came to me after this manner, <hi>bring no more vain Oblations before me, but wait upon the living Motions of my Spirit, to bring forth that Sacrifice which is accepted with me</hi> (out of which I could ſee no Offerings accepted of God, or preſt by Chriſt or his Apoſtles upon any) withal reminding me of what I had formerly felt of the Quickneſs and Sharpneſs of this Word to cut me down from my vain Pleaſures and Paſtimes, which was the ſame that was now come to cut me down from my vain Oblations; by which the Spirit of God was again quencht &amp; limited, &amp; to bring me to that which was more pure &amp; ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, and that the Iſſue of withſtanding this Counſel of God, would be the caſting me under <hi>Deſpair</hi> again, which Words, as I was required, ſo I declared them to one of the Heads of the Family, deſiring the <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Bell</hi> might not ring for me, for that I now felt the Word of the Lord to be really as I had preacht it, as a Sword to cut me down from all vain Oblations, ſo that there was ſtruggling or reſiſting, or kicking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Pricks of this living Word, or ſatisfying
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93225:8"/> of it, but by coming out of all that which I had taken up by Tradition, or Imitation of any, out of its Lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, which was not out of any Diſreſpect to that ſpiritual Prayer &amp; Supplication which was exhorted unto in the Scriptures, which I did the more earneſtly watch unto; but for Fear of offending God by offering that which was become Sin and Iniquity to him, even the <hi>Solemn Aſſembly,</hi> as it is called <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.13. But all this while no man ſtopt me, uor did any Perſecution ſtop me, but I was the more enlarged by it; neither did I act from any Counſel or preſident of any of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple called <hi>Quakers,</hi> from whoſe Converſe I kept my ſelf, ſo as to be acquainted with none of them in that Country, or in any other place where I had lived, and alſo from reading their Books, or going to their Meetings, becauſe of the Danger of Infection that was reported of them; and when a Servant that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the Family, where I was, inclined to go among them, I diſwaded her from it: And now having laid down all at the Feet of God in a Readineſs to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him whitherever he would lead me, I enquired of the Lord what was the Way, and People, and Foundation that he would eſtabliſh and ſet up in the Room of what he had pulled down? and the Lord ſhewed me, and cauſed me to declare the ſubſtance of it to the Family, that according to the Viſion of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> in the ſix firſt verſes of the ſecond chapter, <note place="margin">Read ver. 1, and 2.</note> 
               <hi>That he was now come to eſtabliſh the Spiritual Mountain of his Houſe, a Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which Chriſt ſet up in the Dayes of his Fleſh, not only over the Mountains of</hi> Samaria <hi>and</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>but over all the Mountains and Hills which have ſince riſen up in the Apoſtacy, under what Form or
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93225:8"/> Denomination ſoever, in all which Mountains and Hills there was no Mountain of the Lord's Houſe, where he, had his Reſidence and Dwelling, and therefore he would e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh this Mountain for his Houſe, unto which all the Nations (where the Enemy had ſet up his Mountains and Houſe, in which he had his Seat) ſhould flow, ſo that there ſhould be no other Mountain or Houſe of the Lord, but this alone, which ſhould in time make the other Mountains de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate, as without Inhabitants, which Mountain man in all his Might, Strength and Wiſdom, ſhould have none of the Glory of the Eſtabliſhment or Exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation thereof, but the Lord alone, whoſe Houſe it was, who would be known to be the God of</hi> Jacob, <hi>that was come forth to ſupplant and overturn the lofty Mountains and Hills, and all that dwelt therein, by ſuch a poor deſpiſed People as</hi> Jacob <hi>was.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Read v. 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And that according to the Prophet's Viſion, <hi>The Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that came to this Mountain of the Lord's Houſe were gone up into a higher State of ſupplanting and overcoming, then was known in any of the other Mountains and Hills; &amp; as they had the higheſt and freeſt Miſſion &amp; Authority, ſo they had the higheſt Meſſage and call,</hi> to wit, <hi>to come up to the Teachings of the God of</hi> Jacob, <hi>who was come to ſupplant and overturn all the Teachers of the Mountains and Hills, whoſe Teachings ſo affected thoſe that came un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, as that they were reſolved to walk in no other Paths or Wayes, but what the God of</hi> Jacob <hi>taught them, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their Language</hi> (we will walk) <hi>nor would they go back any more to the Mountains and Hills where the Lord had no houſe or dwelling, nor no teaching of the poor and needy how to ſupplant and overcome their Enemies; for that now they were come to an higher and better Mountain, which was as</hi> Zion <hi>and</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>where
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93225:9"/> the Infallible Word and Law of God was revealed and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven forth, as it was to</hi> Jacob, <hi>who had no other Written Word or Law to walk by,</hi> read ver. 4.</p>
            <p>It was ſhewed me, <hi>That by and through this People</hi> (who were now come) <hi>The Lord would cauſe his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Rebukes to be poured out upon all the Swords and Spears which were uſed to force the People to, or to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them in the Mountains and Hills, or from coming to the Mountain of the Lord's Houſe, which needed not any Sword or Spear to eſtaliſh or exalt it, or to force the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that were ready and free of themſelves to flow unto it. And that the Lord would alſo indue this People, as he did</hi> Jacob, <hi>with ſo much Thriftineſs and Prudence, as not to waſte or throw away what might be improved for the good of the Creation, ſo that, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they ſhould not make any Spoyl upon the Body by the Sword and Spear, ſo neither ſhould they waſte the Swords that had ſpoyled, but rather beat them into Plow-ſhares, and the ſpears into pruning-hooks and ſo turn deſtructive Weapons into uſeful Inſtruments, for the publick proſperity of the Nations, unto which they ſhould become a Bleſsing, as</hi> Jacob <hi>and his Seed was: That their Faith and Belief ſhould be ſo high, as that the Judgments and Rebukes of the Lord ſhould never ceaſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Proclaiming this Mountain, until (Supplanter like) it had brought down all Nations, Parties and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions to ceaſe from riſing up one againſt another; and that the Concord and Agreement of the Nations ſhould be ſo great, as that (the Houſe of the Lord being now come, for which they fought) they ſhould learn War no more, nor ſeek to take up any Sword or Spear, which they had beaten into Plow-ſhares and pruning-hooks, which now they were to learn the uſe of, as that which ſhould abide when the Sword and all the Trade and Traffick of the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93225:9"/> that was for War, ſhould ceaſe and come to in End,</hi> read ver. 5.</p>
            <p>It was ſhewed me, as theſe verſes opened one after another, that the People unto whom I was to go, <hi>were,</hi> as to the Nobility of their Off ſpring, <hi>of the Houſe and Family of</hi> Worm Jacob <hi>the</hi> Supplanter, <hi>and that as</hi> Jacob <hi>did, ſo they ſhould alſo ſupplant the Nations, by the moſt unlikelieſt Wayes and Means,</hi> viz. <hi>Not by Rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as</hi> Eſau, <hi>who was the Father of the Mountains, but by Smoothneſs and Gentleneſs; not by Pollicy and Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningneſs, as</hi> Eſau, <hi>but by Plainneſs and Simplicity; not by going from Home &amp; ſeeking and toyling abroad, like</hi> Eſau <hi>the</hi> Hunter, <hi>but by quiet abiding in their Tents and Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations; not by Might nor Force of outward Weapons, in the Diſuſe of which</hi> Jacob <hi>was ſingular from his Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, but by Strength of Prayers &amp; ſpiritual Wreſtlings,</hi> which is atteſted by ſeveral learned Men, upon <hi>Gen.</hi> 48.22. <hi>not by any bloody Plots or Conſpiracies, nor by any Confederacy with the Houſe of</hi> Levi, <hi>the Father of the Prieſts, in whoſe Houſe</hi> (<hi>but not in</hi> Jacob<hi>'s) the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Cruelty were found,</hi> upon whom <hi>Jacob</hi> pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out an irrevocable Curſe, and in the Hatred and Antipathy of his innocent Mind charged his Soul, not to enter into his Aſſembly, nor his Honour to be united to him—Not by the Dictates or Example of any precedent men or Scripture that was not then written, but by following the Guidance of God's Word and Spirit, which brought him up over all Oppoſition &amp; Aſſaults to <hi>Bethel,</hi> the Place of Worſhip and Sacrifice unto God, in which Reſpects <hi>Jacob</hi> was ſingled out by the Holy Ghoſt, as a Lively Type of the People whom God would call and raiſe up from a low Degree in the laſt Dayes.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:93225:10"/>
            <p>And I had not only a ſight of this People by their Doctrine, Practice and Off-ſpring before mentioned, but alſo <hi>By the Principle by which they ſhould walk, and from which they ſhould receive Power to ſupplant and overturn, which was the</hi> Light of the Lord, <hi>which</hi> Light <hi>their Meſſage ſhould be to call the People to,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Read ver. 5.</note> O Houſe of <hi>Jacob,</hi> come ye, and let us walk in the Light of the Lord, <hi>which Light was ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to bring them off from the Mountains and Hills up to the Houſe of God, where the God of</hi> Jacob <hi>teacheth and giveth forth his Word and Law, which is not the Light of man's Dictates or Examples but the Light of the God of</hi> Jacob, <hi>by which</hi> Jacob <hi>walked, and was taught to ſupplant &amp; overcome; ſo that, as this Mountain came to be eſtabliſhed on the Top of all the Mountains and Hills, ſo the Light alſo ſhould be eſtabliſhed and exalted on the Top of all the Foundations, Rules and Principles of the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains that walked by Tradition: The Sufficiency of which Light ſhould not be only manifeſted by the Benefit of them that walk therein, but by the Forſaking of thoſe that ſhould reject and deſpiſe it, the Cauſe of which ſhould be their being filled and repleniſht with ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Read ver. 6. to the end.</note> 
               <hi>ſo that there ſhould be no more room to receive Chriſt in his ſpiritual Appearance, as a Light, then there was room in the Inn, which was filled and repleniſht with other Gueſts, to receive him in his outward Appearance, becauſe of which God would cauſe his Judgments and Rebukes to paſs upon the Treaſures and Idols, and Glory of the Mountains, which had reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht and filled up their hearts, ſo as to ſtain their Glory, until he had left them not a Staff or a Stay to lean upon, &amp; had cauſed the Mark of his Diſpleaſure to paſs upon the Mighty Man, the Man of War, the Captain of fifty, the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93225:10"/> Judge, the Prophet, the Prudent, the Counſellor, the Cunning Artificer and Eloquent Orator, ſo that no Rank or Degree of men, that had deſpiſed this Mountain or Light ſhould be able by all their Power &amp; Prudence, Art or Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to eſcape the Stroke of the God of</hi> Jacob, <hi>who is come forth in his ſpiritual Hoſt &amp; Army to Supplant and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, until the Lofty Looks of Man, that looks ſcornful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon this People and Light, as</hi> Eſau <hi>did upon</hi> Jacob, <hi>be brought low, and his Haughtineſs be abaſed, and he made of no account, that ſo the God of</hi> Jacob <hi>may alone be Reverenced and exalted in his own Houſe and People, and there be no Mountain, Houſe or Principle left to ſtand in Competition with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus being the ſecond time ranſomed through Judgment, and the Way of the Lord ſo plainly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened unto me, I could no longer delay ſeeking out ſome of the People here deſcribed, whom I was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced were come, but I knew not where to find, but as the Lord put it into my Heart to go to ſuch a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor's Houſe, and deſire him to ſend for one of the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> which I did, and when I came to him, and enquired of him concerning that People he told me, <hi>There were in that Village but Three or Four Families of Poor Inconſiderable People, that were mean in Ability, and that the Men were at Harveſt, but their Wives were at Home;</hi> So I ſent for one of them, whom when ſhe came, I took ſtrict notice of her Carriage and Words; and when I had diſcourſed with her about the Light of Chriſt, which they profeſſed in them, and what Benefit they reaped by walking in it, to overcome their Spiritual Enemies, and to work Salvation for them; her Teſtimony ſo ſuited to what the Lord had before ſhew'd unto me,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93225:11"/> and the Gravity and Saviour of her Language and Deportment was ſuch; counſelling me, <hi>To mind the Truth in me, which would bring me further, as I kept low and obedient to the Croſs of Chriſt Jeſus, for that the Lord had a further Work in his due time to do in me and by me;</hi> which Advice was of God, ſo that I could not but confeſs to the Wiſdom ſhe was guided by, which I eſteemed the more for her <hi>outward Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Plainneſs:</hi> and afterwards, as I diſcourſed with her Husband, <hi>a plain Man,</hi> in his Return from Labour, I found, <hi>that their whole Stay and Support was in the Spirit of the Lord, whoſe Teachings and Leadings they waited for at all times, to guide them out of all Evil Thoughts, Words and Works, into all Truth, in which God alone is worſhipped;</hi> which Teſtimony beſt reached my Conſcience, and anſwered the Spirit of Truth in my own Heart, the manner of whoſe ſtirring &amp; movings from a Child, and of its being quenched, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to be raiſed again, I have before declared of, concerning which I never met with any that teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo feelingly and experimentally of the inward Work of <hi>Redemption</hi> and <hi>Regeneration</hi> by Chriſt Jeſus, in the Senſe of which my Heart was upon the firſt Meeting firmly united to them, ſo as from that time not to look back any more unto any thing the Lord had called me out of, but reſolved, <hi>to take up my Lot with them,</hi> which I ſignified to my <hi>Relations.</hi> And when I returned in the Evening from this <hi>plain people</hi> and came in before the <hi>Counſellor</hi> and his Wife with my uſual Language and Deportment, which was out of the Croſs of Chriſt, which I knew was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to the <hi>plain Language of the Scriptures, and Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of Chriſt and his Apoſtles,</hi> I was ſoon reproved
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93225:11"/> for Reſpect of Perſons, and loſt my Peace and Life that was raiſed in me, and ſo went to my Bed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Judgment, crying unto the Lord, <hi>Not to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his Peace and Comfort from me, nor to let this put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtop to what he intented further to make known unto me,</hi> promiſing <hi>to obey him, if he would ſpare me to the Morning;</hi> which when I was riſen and had ſeated my ſelf, the <hi>Counſellour</hi>'s Wife, whom I well eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and reſpected, came into the Chamber, unto whom, becauſe of the Fear of the Lord, I uſed that <hi>plain Language</hi> and <hi>Department</hi> which I was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of, in which, though it may ſeem as a ſmall thing, I had great Joy and Peace; and when I was asked the <hi>Occaſion of that Change and Alteration that was in me,</hi> I told her to this effect, <hi>That I was now confirmed by Converſe, that the People which I preached of to be the</hi> Houſe of Jacob, <hi>the Plain Man, were come, the Way of whoſe Supplanting ſhould be by that which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Foeliſhneſs and Simplicity unto the Nations:</hi> After which it went forth into the Family and Country, <hi>That I was become a Quaker.</hi> And the next Firſt Day, being alone at Home, I was required, <hi>To go to the Place where I firſt ſpake with the Woman, and to ſeek out their Meeting;</hi> which I did, and when I came, I found a few People met together in a ſerious manner, wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Lord, among whom (though few, if any words were utter'd) I felt that <hi>Preſence</hi> and <hi>Power of God</hi> in which I had more Satisfaction then in my own Preaching and Praying—and ſuch a room and place this People had with me (as ſtill they have) that I thought no time too long which I ſpent with them, or Pains too much to go to their Meetings, which was far diſtant from that Place; and the more. I
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93225:12"/> was acquainted with them, the more I was united to them, eſpecially after that I had heard their Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and Declarations, and was a Witneſs of the Life and Power that accompanied <hi>Mean Illiterate</hi> Perſons, ſuch as the firſt that I heard was, I was the more joyned unto them, whoſe Prayers and Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations were more prevalent to bring me unto, and keep me in the Light, then all the Prayers and Faſts of thoſe that deny its Guidance were to keep me from it.</p>
            <p>Thus, according to my earneſt Deſires to the Lord, to bring forth the Work which he would e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh in the room of that which he had pulled down before I went out of that Family, I was for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 2 <hi>weeks</hi> among them in a <hi>teſtimony</hi> to the <hi>truth,</hi> in the Riſings of which I felt more and more <hi>freedom</hi> to be witneſſed from my <hi>Soul's enemies,</hi> and a drawing me again into a watchfulneſs over my own thoughts words and actions, that nothing might ariſe or work in my Heart but what was of God, who was now come to judge down every Evil Thought and Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in the firſt Motion and Riſe of it; ſo that though there was an Abatement of that Bodily Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, which profiteth not, yet there was an Increaſe of Inward Exerciſe to keep a Conſcience void of Offence, not only in the Sight of Man, who lookt at the Outward Appearance, but alſo in the Sight of God, that ſearched the Heart. And in that Family I met with much <hi>Chriſtian</hi>-like Forbearance &amp; Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, not out of any Reſpect to the People and Principle, which they eſteemed too mean and low, but out of Reſpect to that Uprightneſs which they believed to be in me: And now the time of our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93225:12"/> being come, in which I muſt leave them, which (becauſe of that Love and Endearedneſs that had been between us) it was hard to do, but that my Heart was taken up with Chriſt's being come to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive me to himſelf, and to dwell and walk in me as his <hi>houſe</hi> and <hi>temple,</hi> for which End he had ſeparated &amp; called me out from all that was defiled: And ſince I could no longer perform the Office of a <hi>Chaplain,</hi> as it was expected of me, which if I could they deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red no other, they were willing to give me Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, according to our Agreement for the time that I had been among them upon a double Account, <hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>Tutouring their Children,</hi> and of <hi>Preaching:</hi> As to the <hi>Teaching the Children,</hi> I was free to take Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; but as for <hi>Preaching,</hi> notwithſtanding the Money was told out, and I was urged and preſſed to receive it, I was forbidden by the Lord to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and ſo left it. But to clear the Family of all Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitions &amp; Jealouſies that might ariſe in any touching the Ground of my leaving them, I conſented upon the firſt Motion thereof to leave a Certificate, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying to all that might be concerned, <hi>That I left the Family only upon the Account of ſome higher Diſcovery of Truth on my part, not apprehending it to be the Will of the Lord to be worſhipped any otherwiſe then in Spirit and Truth, and that as to Outward Encouragements, they rather exceeded then came ſhort of my Expectation.</hi> And thus in pure Love and Deſires of the Spiritual Welfare of every one, I left that Family, which next to my own Relations were dear to me, who had a full Sight and Experience of my Converſation, as to the Work and Dealings of the Lord with me in that Day. This was about the 7th Moneth of the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93225:13"/> Year 1673. After which I came forward to my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, among whom I knew not one that was inclined to the Truth, who might ſtand with me in a Teſtimony for it, but all Oppoſed it, and joyned with their Teachers againſt it, with whom notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, as I ſtood innocently in the Counſel of God, which led me to yield true Submiſſion and Honour to them next to himſelf, I found way made for my Reception; and alſo opened the Hearts of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple unto me, to whom I was a Stranger, but as the Lord gave them a ſenſe of that Upright Deſire of Truth and Righteouſneſs which only brought me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, in whoſe Meetings I waited as one of the Meaneſt and Loweſt of them for about twelve Moneths, ſitting under the Droppings and Diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of that Life and Power, which the Lord was pleaſed to ſill others with in the Meeting, &amp; to grow daily more and more (as it is daily my Endeavour) in the inward Experience of the Redeeming, Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying and Quickening Virtue of the Truth, which (in the ſenſe of that Love of God in bringing me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong this People, to eat of the Bread of Life, when ſo many Wiſe and Prudent were left behind, feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon Husks) often broke my Heart, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Deſires in me, <hi>That I might never more appear out of the living Stirrings and movings of the Spirit &amp; Life of Chriſt, nor ſtay behind it when it did move.</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which it pleaſed the Lord in his own time (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my own and others Travail and Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation) to cauſe his Life to break forth in me ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in a few words of Prayer, ſometimes of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, in which the Lord gave me Power and Faithfulneſs to eaſe my ſelf, and my Words return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93225:13"/> not to me again, but had entrance; and as I kept low and humble, giving Honour and Glory to Chriſt alone in his Appearance, ſo I ſelt the Increaſe of that Authority and Life, which made way in the Hearts of them to whom I was ſent, in whoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences it is my deſire to ſtand recommended, and to be felt of them who are in Life, as a Savour of Life unto Life.</p>
            <p>And thus the Lord having raiſed me up, and ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me through much Weakneſs and Labour unto this Day to ſee the Deſire of my Soul accompliſhed in great Meaſure, according to my Faith when I firſt laid down my Miniſtry; I do ſtill wait (in Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the Will of the Lord) for the Day, when that breathing Seed of God, which is yet left in the dead and lifeleſs Profeſſions, may become ripe for the Harveſt, then ſhall there be no Want of Reap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, who ſhall put in their Sickles, and gather them into the Houſe which God hath provided for to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive all that are low and poor in their own Eyes, for want of Power and Strength to overcome that which letteth &amp; hindereth their perfect Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; into which Houſe God hath called me, as a Fore-Runner of Thouſands that are yet ungathered, unto which being come up, I can't go back or down unto them, but can freely ſerve the loweſt of them by living Supplications to the Great Shepherd of the Sheep, for the bringing them into that Fold, where he makes his Flocks that were wearied and driven from Mountain to Hill, to reſt at Noon in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of their Beloved, whoſe Tents they need no longer enquire after, or go to the Watch men of the Night for Direction, but by the Light of the Lord
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93225:14"/> are they brought up to <hi>Bethel,</hi> the Houſe of the God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> where they deſire forever to dwell, and offer unto the God of their Redemption, Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Deliverance, as I do, the Sacrifice of Praiſe and of Thankſgiving for evermore.</p>
            <p>And now I ſhall ſhut up all with the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of the Paſtor of that <hi>Independant.</hi> Congregation of which I was a Member, and walkt with for ſeveral years, who (beſt among them) knew the bent of my Heart, who in his <hi>Letter</hi> to my <hi>Mother</hi> ſoon after my Convincement of the Truth, gives this Teſtimony of the Grounds of my leaving them to come to this People, in which he hath confirmed what I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-mentioned; his words are theſe, <hi>The great Stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling-block to him hath been, our Looſe, Low and Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Converſation:</hi> And is not Looſneſs, Lowneſs and Earthlineſs Stumbling block enough, eſpecially in them that profeſs to be Members of Chriſt Jeſus, and look for Salvation by him, and to be gathered out of the World? He may well call it Great; What can lay a greater Stumbling-block in the Way of the Upright, then to make ſo high a Profeſſion a Cloak and Covering for ſo much Sin and Iniquity? Would it not be far better and more Honour to Chriſt, to ceaſe profeſſing of him, which doth but make them the greater Stumbling-blocks, until they have departed from theſe Iniquities? And is not this enough to acquit me from ſeparating from ſuch Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies and Congregations, that are thus poluted? Further, he ſaith, <hi>He is earneſt to get up to More Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualneſs then he ſees among us:</hi> And muſt I be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented in ſo many places as a <hi>deluded deceived Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:93225:14"/> and <hi>one that is fallen from the Faith,</hi> and <hi>apoſtatized to Error,</hi> and <hi>a Saddener of the Hearts of the Upright,</hi> and prayed and faſted for, as ſuch, and all for leaving of ſuch People as are Looſe, Low and Earthly, to get up to more Spiritualneſs? Or can I look upon ſuch as true Friends to my Soul, as would hinder me from ſo good an Exchange? Further, he ſaith, <hi>Which he apprehends is to be found among this People:</hi> Yea, I do more then apprehend it; for I have felt and experienced for ſome years that Spiritualneſs to be among them, which keeps them that walk in it from Looſneſs, Lowneſs and Earthlineſs; ſo that I have no Deſire to return to them whoſe Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are ſo looſe, &amp;c. as he confeſſeth. Further, he ſaith, <hi>I am perſwaded, this is that which hath carried him among them, more then any Reſpect that he hath to their odd Opinions:</hi> Here he hath bound all with his Perſwaſion from that certain Knowledge he had of me for many years, in which he knew my Bent was after Spiritualneſs and Heavenly-mindedneſs; and herein he hath ſpoken the Truth of me, <hi>viz.</hi> That it was Looſneſs, Lowneſs and Earthlineſs that ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and drew me off from them; and that it was with deſire of more Spiritualneſs that I came among this People, and my Deſire hath been therein large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwered, to the Joy and Satisfaction of my Soul. Further, he continueth to ſay, <hi>If we gain this by his Fall, to be provoked to more Heavenlineſs and Spiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and to ſavour leſs of this Earth, we ſhall be Gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers by his Loſs:</hi> Here he ſhould have minded his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Expreſſion and Perſwaſion, and have conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, whether the Lord doth ſuffer ſuch to fall whoſe great Stumbling is at Looſneſs, Lowneſs and Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:93225:15"/> and who are earneſt to get up to more Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualneſs, which is more according to the Will of God: Or are they not fallen and loſt, who according to his Confeſſion, are ſtill where they were many years ago, after all his Preaching and Praying, are not got up above their Looſeneſs, Lowneſs &amp; Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs; whom he preſſeth, and indeed it is high time for them all to manifeſt better Fruits of their profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and to ſavour leſs of this Earth, which hath been the Cauſe of my leaving of them, and to get up to that Spiritualneſs and Heavenlineſs, where they will find me, and ſo in this Spiritualneſs we ſhall be united again. But has not the <hi>cauſe</hi> of this <hi>unprofitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> or <hi>ſtanding at a ſtay</hi> bin for want of coming to that Grace which is ſufficient to teach all that learn of it, to deny All [mark, <hi>All</hi>] Ungodlineſs, and All worldly Luſts, which makes them Stumbling-blocks in the Way of others, that ſo through the denying of theſe, they might come to live ſoberly, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and godly, not only hereafter, but in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Evil World, and ſo not ſtumble, but gain others by their Converſation, without which all Verbal Confeſſion and Acknowledgments are vain and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and leaves them no better then they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:93225:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
